<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Selfe-satisfaction occasionally taught the citizens in the lecture as St. Magnes neere London-bridge. By Francis Tayler, M. of A. and pastour of Clapham.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Francis, 1590-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843222</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 586:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Selfe-satisfaction occasionally taught the citizens in the lecture as St. Magnes neere London-bridge. By Francis Tayler, M. of A. and pastour of Clapham.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Francis, 1590-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton, for Robert Bird, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bible, in St. Laurence-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XIV, 14 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:1"/>
            <p>SELFE-SATISFACTION Occaſionally taught the Citizens in the Lecture At St. <hi>Magnes</hi> neere <hi>London-bridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By FRANCIS TAYLER, <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>A.</hi> and Paſtour of <hi>Clapham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Norton,</hi> for <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bird,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Bible, in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>-Lane. 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>p. 8. from the duty of piety, from the duties. p. 12. roote of Apoſtcy, Apoſtacy. p. 14. couered with a bate, a baite. p. 31. playes it the midſt, in the midſt. Nothing cannot ſecure, can ſecure. p. 37. marg. <hi>Shaddac, Shaddai, lo dac, ol dai.</hi> p. 43. marg. <hi>ta perton. peri tôn pragmat ôn. Is. Ib.</hi> p. 45. that giues a good, hee giues.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:2"/>
            <head>TO THE FRVIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVLL VINE, AND pleaſant Oliue plants the Lady <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Pye,</hi> Wife to the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Sir <hi>Walter Pye,</hi> Atturny of the Court of Wards, and her Children, Captaine <hi>Criſpe,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Samuel Criſpe,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Tobias Criſpe,</hi> and their wiues, M<hi rend="sup">ris.</hi> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocke,</hi> and her Husband.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a moſt firme demonſtration of Gods excellency that although all creatures depend on him, yet is there ſuch a Sea of goodneſſe in God, that is neuer dryed vp. No one creature, not the greateſt is able to vphold it ſelfe. God is euery way ſufficient of himſelfe and could giue himſelfe full ſatisfaction, if their neuer had beene a world. The happieſt of the creatures is hee that comes neereſt to God. He that can ſubſist (if he be put to it) without any creatures helpe, and depends ſoly on the Creator. This excellent condition can none attaine vnto, but he that hath, and knowes he hath a speciall intereſt in God. So fleeting are all worldly contentments, that nothing can bee firme that is built vpon them: the times in which wee liue are the laſt dayes: the Churches full of warres, blood and troubles: our ſinnes haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that the cloudes of affliction ſhould croſſe the Seas to follow vs.<note place="margin">Pſal. 61.2.</note> Happy is he therefore that is ſet vpon a rocke
<pb facs="tcp:7937:3"/>higher then himſelfe. Happy is hee that can ſay, and ſay feelingly,<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.11.</note> 
               <hi>In God haue I put my truſt, I will not bee afrayd what man can doe vnto mee.</hi> Happy is hee that finds an Arke at home that can hide him when the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are farre aboue the highest mountaines.<note place="margin">Gen. 7.19, 20.</note> Happy can he neuer aſſuredly be that fals ſhort of this, and ſettles his rest on any thing vnder the Sunne. He must come to <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> experimentall concluſion, <hi>Vanity of vanities, all is vanity.</hi> The ſubiect of theſe paines is ſo much the more worthy acceptation, becauſe it is a ladder that leads to the happieſt and ſurest condition. If in the handling I fall ſhort of other mens expectation, I ſhall be glad to ſee other men handle it more exactly. To my ſelfe it is ſome comfort, I haue written that which hath ſtayd me in many, &amp; through Gods grace may stay me in any tryals. You and yours Madam haue I choſen for the Patrons of this worke, in regard of that ancient acquaintance that hath beene betweene vs: Your Family hath left mee as many tokens of your loue as I haue Children. That ſhort ſpace which I liued in the City how much I was indebted to you, I forbeare to ſpeake, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire rather to ſpeake to God to requite it. And ſince I haue receiued much comfort, and many kind encouragements and remembrance from your and their ourteſie. I haue not ſeene a Family in the City to my beſt remembrance which God hath ſo plentifully watred with ſpirituall and temporall ſhowers of bleſſings in the Roote and in all the Branches. Your houſe and poſterity are a remarkable example of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of benediction and multiplication to them that feare him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.</note> If this labour may be pleaſing and profitable to you, I ſhall hope it will be ſo to others. So I leaue it as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall token of my neuer-dying affection to your Family, wiſhing you, what the Title offers you, <hi>Selfe-ſatiſfaction.</hi> Leſſe I cannot wiſh you, more I need not. Let it ſuffice then that I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Chriſtian obſeruance</hi> Francis Tayler.</signed>
               <dateline>Clapham, <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 27. 1633.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:3"/>
            <head>Selfe-Satisfaction.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 14.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Backſlider in heart ſhall be ſatisfied with his owne waies, and a good man from himſelfe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely Beloued in our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vncertainety of all worldly comforts may force euery one of vs to ſeeke for ſatisfaction from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. The fleeting of the beſt of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward contentments may make him looke for his beſt contentment within. The Text tels vs of a double ſatisfaction: a bad one, and a good one. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fills the owner with a world of miſeries; the latter poſſeſſes the enioyer with a heauen of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Prouerbes haue no coherence. It is as ſuperfluous to giue a connexion to Prouerbes as to put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rime. Both detract from the maieſty of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes, which are golden and compendious ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that giue ſatisfaction themſelues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne a world of good matter in few words within themſelues, and without depending one vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:7937:4"/>And becauſe they haue no coherence to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate them, they haue the more neede of carefull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. A great helpe for their expoſition, is their oppoſition. For though they cleaue not one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet the parts in many of them are one oppoſite to another, and contraries placed one by another illuſtrate each other. Beauty is neuer ſo beautifull, as when deformity ſtands in oppoſition to it.</p>
            <p>Therefore the wiſe God placed in the Elements contrary qualities. He made heate predominant in one Element, cold in another; dryneſſe in one, moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in another. Therefore doth he depriue his beſt ſeruants of many ſingular mercies, that they may the better vnderſtand the worth of them by the want of them. The oppoſition then will helpe vs in the expoſition of this Prouerbe.</p>
            <p>Yet muſt you not imagine that this oppoſition of the parts takes any thing away from the truth of eyther part, becauſe the oppoſition is in diuers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. To ſay <hi>Salomon did fall to idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Salomon did not fall to idolatry,</hi> cannot be both true. The one detracts from the verity of the other. But to ſay <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon did fall to idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Dauid did not fall to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> are both true, for we ſpeake of diuers ſubiects differing in their courſes. The one is ſo farre from detracting from the truth of the other, that it rather illuſtrates the ſame. <hi>Salomons</hi> fall makes <hi>Dauids</hi> conſtancy the more admirable, and <hi>Dauids</hi> conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy makes <hi>Salomons</hi> fall the more diſcommendable. Thus ſhall we the better vnderſtand the good ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction that a godly man hath from himſelfe, when we firſt conceiue the ſorry ſatisfaction that a wicked
<pb facs="tcp:7937:4"/>man findes from his owne waies. But before I come to the logicall oppoſition of the parts, giue me leaue to ſpend ſome time in the grammaticall expoſition of the words; for expoſition is the ground of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and obſeruation is the ground of applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <q>The backſlider.</q>
            <p>The Hebrew is word for word, <hi>He that is turned backe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sug. <hi>part praet,</hi> auerſus.</note> It poynts out vnto vs the prouocations of the world, whereby men are turned away from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God. Hee that is turned backe, finds ſome thing to turne him, beſides the crookedneſſe of his owne diſpoſition.</p>
            <q>In heart.</q>
            <p>This word ſhewes vs the internall originall of all backſliding, which is the heart. In vaine were all the prouocations of the world, if the heart ſtood it out. But when the heart once faints, then is the whole man ſoone turned backeward.</p>
            <q>Shall be ſatisfied.</q>
            <p>This ſeemes an hard phraſe: men are ſatisfied with good things, not with euill.<note place="margin">Meton: effecti.</note> It muſt then bee vnderſtood by a figure of the effect for the cauſe. <hi>He ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> that is, <hi>he ſhall be filled,</hi> for ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the cauſe of ſatisfaction. An euill man ſhall be as full of miſery as a good man is of contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe when he is ſatisfied with it.</p>
            <q>With his owne waies.</q>
            <p>His waies here intended are not the footſteps of his body, but the actions of his life.<note place="margin">Metaphora.</note> It is vſuall in Scripture to compare the courſe of man vnto a walke. <hi>Bleſſed are the vndefiled in the way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.1.</note> Bad actions
<pb facs="tcp:7937:5"/>are alſo compared to bad and filthy wayes, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the counſell of the vngodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 1.1,</note> The intent of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude is to ſhew our ſtrangneſſe by our birth, our reſtleſnes in our life, and our progreſſe to our death. Our birth is the entrance into our pilgrimage, the beginning of our iourney. Our life is our trauaile, a reſtleſſe and weary courſe. Our death is the end of our iourney: it brings vs to our euerlaſting home. There is a double home. Good men haue a good home: this was the dwelling of the <hi>Corinthians, We haue an houſe eternall in the Heauens.</hi> Bad men haue a bad home:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> that is the habitation of trayterous <hi>Iudas,</hi> who left his Apoſtleſhip to goe <hi>to his owne place.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 1.25.</note> His waies then are his actions: but not all his actions, onely his wicked actions: for God doth oftentimes reward euill men for morall good actions, and not plague them.<note place="margin">1 Kings. 21.29. 2 Kings. 10.30 <hi>Synecdoche gener is.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Ahab</hi> puts off the plague by his humiliation. So <hi>Iehu</hi> by ſlaying the worſhippers of <hi>Baal</hi> ſettles the Kingdome on his poſterity to the fourth generation. The actions then of the backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that trouble him are his ſinfull actions. Neyther is it his ſinfull actions that doe diſquiet him, but his troubles and miſeries that follow vpon his ſins. He is not weary of ſinning, but of being miſerable; or at leaſt he is no further weary of ſinne, then as it brings miſery vpon him.<note place="margin">Meton. conſae.</note> So then his waies are his actions, his actions are his ſinfull actions, his ſinfull actions are the miſeries that follow vpon them, and theſe are they that perpetually vexe him.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:7937:5"/> And a good man from himſelfe.</q>
            <p>Theſe words are diuerſly read, becauſe of the want of the Verbe, the double Prepoſition,<note place="margin">Min <hi>and</hi> Gnal.</note> and the diuers ſignifications of them. The vulgar Latine reads it thus: <hi>And a good man ſhall be ouer him.</hi> That is to ſay For his backſliding God will make him a ſlaue to him that is good. <hi>Trimellius,</hi> the French Bible, and the Geneua Engliſh Bible thus, <hi>But a good man ſhall depart from him.</hi> That is, a good man foreſeeing or ſeeing the miſeries, that follow the ſinfull courſes of a backſlider, will auoyde his company. The latter tranſlation reads it farre better, <hi>And a good man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelfe.</hi> The ſafeſt way of addition where a word is wanting, is to ſupply it out of the former part of the ſentence. Seeing then the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the verſe ſpeakes of an euill mans ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his euill waies, the coneluſion muſt needes ſpeake of a good mans ſatisfaction from himſelfe. The Hebrew phraſe is <hi>from with himſelfe,</hi> that is, from thoſe things that are within him; or, that God hath beſtowed vpon him. So S. <hi>Paul, Not I,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>but the grace of God which was with me.</hi> Meaning the grace which God had beſtowed vpon him: And it is worth your noting that the wiſe man doth not ſay, <hi>The backſlider ſhall bee ſatisfied from his owne waies, and a good man from his:</hi> leaſt any man ſhould imagine, that a good man merits his ſatisfaction, as a bad man doth his vexation. Neyther doth the Hebrew phraſe ſay, <hi>From himſelfe,</hi> barely, but <hi>from with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> that is from thoſe graces that GOD hath giuen him: leaſt any man ſhould maintaine the full and free power of mans will, as if a good
<pb facs="tcp:7937:6"/>mans ſatisfaction came as orginally from himſelfe, as a bad mans vexation comes from the corruption of his owne will. Thus it teacheth vs to attribute the beginning of an euill mans miſery to his owne backſliding, and the beginning of a good mans ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Gods grace and bounty. Who this good man is that receiues ſatisfaction from Gods grace within him, I neede not ſtand to vnfold, the oppoſition in the text ſhewes it plainely: It is hee that is no backeſlider, but keepes him cloſe to Gods Commandements.</p>
            <p>The ſumme then of all is this, Hee that is by the prouocations of the world drawne away from that ſeruice, that he owes to Almighty God, ſhall bring ſo many troubles vpon himſelfe, that hee ſhall be weary of his life. But hee that walkes conſcionably in that way, that God hath appoynted him to walke in, ſhall bee ſo inriched with the graces of Gods Spirit, that hee ſhall be able to giue ſatisfaction to himſelfe, though he be forſaken by all the world.</p>
            <p>God hath two ſorts of children, and he hath two portions for them, both ſet out in the words of the text. Some are rebellious children, nouriſhed by God, but rebelling againſt him. Their portion is miſery flowing from their owne ſinnes. Others are obedient children not faſhioning themſelues accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the luſts of ignorant men:<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.14.</note> and their portion is ſatisfaction ariſing from the grace of God within them. The portion of backſliding children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to our carefull conſiderations theſe</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:6"/>
            <p> Foure parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Perſon. in the firſt word. <hi>The backſlider.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. in the phraſe. <hi>Hee that is turned backe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall internall. in the next word. <hi>In heart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. in the laſt words. <hi>Shall bee filled with his owne waies.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the firſt.</p>
            <p>That there are backſliders is a needleſſe thing for me to prooue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <note place="margin">The perſon.</note> Scripture and experience of all ages prooue it to my hand. My labour muſt be to ſhew who they are, from the particular kinde of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. A backſlider is he that falls away eyther from that good courſe he hath taken, or at leaſt from that good courſe he ought to take.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.12. 2 Pet. 2.21.</note> The latter is a turning out of the right way. The former is a returning to a wrong way.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.9.</note> The one is naturall and common to all both Iewes and Gentiles. It is the eſtate wee are borne in: it is the eſtate they liue and dye in, that know not the Goſpell or the way of ſaluation by Chriſt alone. The other is voluntary,<note place="margin">2 Pet 2, 20,</note> not a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put vpon vs by our parents, but choſen by our ſelues. The one is a fayling in our duety, the other is a falling from our profeſſion. I let paſſe the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall defection, becauſe it is not that which <hi>Salomon</hi> here aimes at, preaching to the backſliding Iewes, not to the wandering Gentiles. Neyther is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for mee to ſpeake of, that ſpeake to ſuch as are beleeuing Chriſtians, not vnbeleeuing heathen by profeſſion. We profeſſe a double duety: the one to
<pb facs="tcp:7937:7"/>God, comprehended in the precepts of the firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: the other to man, contained in the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the ſecond. The profeſſion of a double duety, makes vs ſubiect to a double apoſtaſy. The firſt is a falling from the duety of piety. The ſecond is a falling from morall honeſty. Our falling from duties of piety is eyther a publique, or a priuate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The publike apoſtaſy is the falling from the profeſſion of the true Religion to Idolatry and falſe worſhips: this apoſtaſy the Iſraelits were much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto: <hi>They turned backe and dealt vnfaithfully like their fathers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78 57.58.</note> 
               <hi>they were turned aſide like a deceirfull Bow. For they prouoked him to anger with their high places: and moued him to iealouſie with their grauen images.</hi> Thus dealt they with God vnder their Iudges: they ſerued him in their miſery, but when their Iudges were dead, they returned to idolatry. <hi>And when the Lord raiſed them vp Iudges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudge 2.18.19.</note> 
               <hi>then the Lord was with the Iudge, and deliuered them out of the hand of their enemies all the daies of the Iudge (for it repented the Lord becauſe of their groanings by reaſon of them that oppreſſed and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.) And it came to paſſe when the Iudge was dead, that they returned and corrupted themſelues more then their fathers, in following other Gods to ſerue them, and to bow downe to them: they ceaſed not from their owne doings, nor from their ſtubborn way.</hi> Thus dealt they with God, vnder their Kings: when their Kings were good, they ſerued God, and when they were euill, they ſerued Idols. Such are they that after ſo great light by the preaching of the Goſpell, turne to antichriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the true Religion and fall to popery. Such are they that being taken by the enemies of the
<pb facs="tcp:7937:7"/>Chriſtian name turne <hi>Turkes,</hi> that they may not turne ſlaues. They venture their ſoules to ſaue their bodies, forſake their God to procure their quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Their offence is ſo much the greater, becauſe they not onely leaue Chriſt, but cleaue to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. They not onely forſake God, but ſerue Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan againſt God. Theſe are trayterous ſouldiours, that content not themſelues to faile their Captaine in the heate of the battell, but fight againſt him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly vnder the colour of his knowne Aduerſary. They not onely weaken Gods part what lyes in them, by their Apoſtacy; but alſo ſtrengthen the aduerſe part by their contrary profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The priuate defection is a falling from the practice of thoſe priuate dutyes men haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly performed to the LORD of Hoaſts. Such are they that haue beene carefull of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Morning and Euening in their Families, and daily in their cloſets. But afterward neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect all priuate Prayers, and like bad husbands waſt their owne priuate ſtocke, and looke to liue vpon the publicke charge. Such are they that haue beene zealous for the glory of GOD, but are growne remiſſe, and care not how God bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured. Such are they that haue with patience borne all troubles, as comming from God: but now murmure at the leaſt calamity, as if it came from the Diuell that hated them, and not from God that loued them. Theſe are like to rotten Apples, that when they begin to putrify grow worſe and worſe, till they be good for nothing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:8"/>
            <p> The ſecond fall is from morall honeſty, when men haue beene carefull to liue iuſtly in the world for a time, and afterwards deceiue the expectation of the times, and proue deceitfull themſelues. Yee haue many that haue beene wonderfull iuſt ſeruants, that proue moſt vniuſt maſters: When they were ſeruants they delt truely, for the gaine was their maſters; now they are maſters they deale falſely, for the gaine is their owne. Some children are very quiet in their yonger yeeres, and the delight of their parents, who in their elder yeeres proue moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, and perpetuall vexations to them that with moſt tenderneſſe haue bred them. <hi>Abſolon</hi> and <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niiah</hi> were <hi>Dauids</hi> ioy, when they were children, and <hi>Dauids</hi> annoyances when they were men. Some haue beene famous for deedes of charity in the ſtrongth of their yeeres, that in their dote-age haue beene ſtrangely miſerable, as if they had taken no care for the world, when they were likely to liue long in it, and take care for nothing elſe but the world when they were likely to goe ſoone out of it. Theſe are they that haue ſet God and the world at defiance; they neyther regard to keepe a good conſcience towards God, nor a good name before men: they haue made ſhippewracke of faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards men, and of a good conſcience before God.</p>
            <p>Let vs now come to the ſecond poynt, What may make theſe men to ſlide backe? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">Externall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations to Apoſtaſy.</note> Surely, the manifold prouocations of the world. That they may the better be auoyded, they may be ranked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe particulars. Firſt, the troubles of the
<pb facs="tcp:7937:8"/>world. Man hath a ſtrange paſſion called feare, that will ſmell out danger before it come, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before it be intended. All his care now is to preuent this trouble: whether it be by good meanes or bad, his wiſedome will not forecaſt, becauſe it aimes at nothing, but freedome from imminent danger. Mans nature is very tender: it ſeekes to turne away all manner of hardneſſe. <hi>Peter</hi> eſpies a cloud comming, hee muſt needs deny his Maſter,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.35.70.</note> or beare trouble with him: his ſtout heart that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would dye with him rather then deny him, now will deny him that it may not dye with him. Many a man playes abroad with the Bee, and gathers honey in the ſummer of proſperity, that hides his head within his hiue in the winter of aduerſity.<note place="margin">Iudge 7.3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> If God like <hi>Gideon</hi> ſhould make a proolamation of a war, and ſend backe euery one whoſe heart faileth him, he muſt be contented with ten thou ſand, and let twenty two thouſand goe backe againe to liue in peace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the profits of the world driue many backe from their former forwardneſſe. Deſire is a ſtrong paſſion. It is like a Riuer with a violent cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: no bankes can keepe it in. If it once faſten vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on riches, it cannot eaſily bee pulled off. <hi>Demas</hi> keepes S. <hi>Paul</hi> company a while,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> but in the end for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes him for <hi>the loue of this preſent world.</hi> Religion lookes at another world, her prayers, her plots all looke that way. Couetouſnes lookes at this world, her deuices ayme at nothing but at riches.<note place="margin">Matth. 26.15.</note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Chriſt a while, but afterwards for deſire of gaine leaues him, nay betrayes him. Riches are the
<pb facs="tcp:7937:9"/>thornes that choake the ſeede,<note place="margin">Luke 8.14.</note> ſo that it comes not to perfection. They muſt forſake God that ſerue Mammon,<note place="margin">Math. 6.24.</note> for it is impoſſible to pleaſe both. And no wonder if that bee the roote of Apoſtey, which is <hi>the roote of all euill:</hi> euen the loue of mony, <hi>which while ſome coueted after, they haue erred from the fayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>and pierced themſelues thorow with many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the delights of the world are the ſweete ſinging Syrens, that draw many backe to their vtter ouerthrow. Theſe worke vpon the affection of ioy or delight. A pleaſing affection, but neuer ſatisfied, it neuer ſayth enough:<note place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> the ſweete content that <hi>Lots</hi> wife had in the idle pleaſures of <hi>Sodome</hi> commands her affection: and her affection commands her eyes to looke backe once more to behold the place ſhe ſo well loued. Vnthankfull ſhe ſhews her ſelfe to God that freede her preferring the imaginations of her owne pleaſures before the Commandement of God, and ſtands as a monument to poſterity, a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Salt. Theſe are bewitching temptations and forcible prouocations: it is farre more pleaſing to mans nature to liue at eaſe abounding in pleaſures, then to carke and care labouring for riches. Both withdraw from Gods ſeruice, but that is moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous which withdrawes with moſt contentment to the mind of man.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, euill counſails of others draw many backe from their profeſſions of piety and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. This is the miſchiefe of bad kindred. This is the diſcommodity of bad neyghbourhood. This is the fruite of euill acquaintance. All men
<pb facs="tcp:7937:9"/>deſire to haue their friends like to themſelues; all men wiſh naturally to be as like them whom they loue, as they can. Hence it is that bad counſaile is eaſily giuen, and eaſily taken. The ones tongue is the fire, the others heart is the fuell, that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fily burſts out into a flame.<note place="margin">Numb. 25.18.</note> Thus the <hi>Midianites</hi> vexe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with their wiles: they firſt vſe them courteouſly, draw them into their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo perſwade them both to corporall and ſpirituall fornication. Thus many ſweete diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue beene vndone: and they that might by good aduice haue beene turned to the praiſe of GOD, haue beene made iarring inſtruments of loud impieties. Bad Maſters, euill Tutours, hollow-hearted Guardians, haue ruined many yong mens plyable diſpoſitions with their patrimonies. Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles in a Garden grow not a lone, but produce a multitude of other ſtinging weedes, as bad as themſelues. Phariſes compaſſe Sea and Land to make a Proſelyte,<note place="margin">Math. 23.15.</note> and make him the childe of the Diuell twofolde more then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, euill example is the bane of many: Man is of a ſociable diſpoſition; hee loues not to walke alone, but to goe where others goe before him. Thus euill Rulers vndoe the poore people by their example, and Anceſtours ſeduce their poſterity. It is the piller of the popiſh religion; our fathers li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and dyed in this religion, and ſo will we. Euill counſels ſeduce much, but euill examples much more the likenes of our nature and naturall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes one man ouer forward to imitate another.
<pb facs="tcp:7937:10"/>Ill words are like a hooke couered with a bate, that deceiues one fiſh among many. Ill examples are like nets that take farre more then they let goe. What we ſee other men doe, that we thinke we may doe; and their boldnes in ſinne and freedome from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment duls the edge of Gods threatnings in the mouthes of his Miniſters, and of his curſes red in the Law, becauſe we ſee no puniſhment light vpon them: therefore doe we perſwade our ſelues, that we ſhall eſcape puniſhment as well as they, if we ſin as deepely as they doe. <hi>Peter</hi> diſſembles but a little, and the other Iewes diſſemble with him:<note place="margin">Gal. 2.13.</note> and no maruell, for <hi>Barnabas</hi> himſelfe makes one, and takes part with <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſame diſſimulation. What will bad men doe? how eaſily will they imitate one another in bad waies, when good men are ſo prone to doe it? And thus much for the prouocations, that leade men backeward, that may auoyde them.</p>
            <p>The third poynt conſiderable is the internall ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of backſliding, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <note place="margin">The internall originall of backeſliding.</note> which is the heart. <hi>The backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in heart.</hi> The prouocations of the world may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, but they cannot preuaile, vnleſſe the heart be firſt tainted: the body will neuer turne backe vnleſſe the heart yeeld firſt: therefore God requires all the heart for his ſeruice,<note place="margin">Deut. 10.12.</note> for he knowes well, that when the heart begins to faint, the body will not long ſtand it out. God requires a perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him in the heart as a preſeruatiue againſt diſobedience in the life:<note place="margin">Deut. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>beware thou forget not the Lord thy God in not keeping his Commandements, and Statutes and his iudgements, which I command thee this day.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:7937:10"/>woman deuoures the ſweetnes of the forbidden fruit in her heart, before ſhe taſte of it with her mouth.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>When the woman ſaw that the tree was good for foode, and that it was pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſhe tooke of the fruit thereof, and did eate.</hi> The heart is the receptacle of all euill counſailes that tend vnto defection: whatſoeuer the eye or eare let in, the heart takes it into conſideration: there is the Councell table, where the vnderſtanding, the will, and all the affections conſult and conclude, what ſhall be brought into action, the beginning of all euill actions is there, there is the ſhoppe in which are forged all euill words and wicked deeds before they be ſet forth to ſale in the life. So doth our bleſſed Sauiour teſtifie, <hi>Out of the heart proceede euill thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>falſe witneſſe, blaſphemies.</hi> Though the occaſion of backſliding be from the world, yet the true originall is of our ſelues. <hi>Our Creator who loues what hee hath created, perſecates no man, but him that firſt perſecutes himſelfe. God departs from no man, that doth not firſt depart from God,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> truely teacheth.<note place="margin">A nulle recedit Deus, niſi prius ipſe ab eo rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat <hi>Aug.</hi> de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut docum. <hi>c. 54.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Fulgentius</hi> treading in the ſteppes of <hi>Auguſtine, God,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>would not haue deſtroyed euill men in iudgement, if they had not firſt periſhed through their owne iniquities. Backſliding then from the chiefeſt good to the meaneſt good, this is proper to the ſinner, and his volunt ary euill by which the vniuſt man, deſtroyes himſelfe. And becauſe God is not the authour of this euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dignè homini qui ſe perdidis peccato, reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in tormentis aeterna perditio. <hi>Fulg</hi> de praed. ad Mon. <hi>lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but the peruerſe man; therefore eternall deſtruction is iuſtly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to that man in porments, who hath firſt vndone him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by his wickedneſſe.</hi> There needes now no further
<pb facs="tcp:7937:11"/>ſearch for the true beginning of defection from profeſſion of piety. It is not to be imputed to Gods permiſſion, nor to the worlds prouocation, but the firſt beginning of the act of defection is in mans wauering inclination. Satan ſhould tempt in vaine, and the world prouoke to no purpoſe, if mans heart did not yeeld to the temptations of the one, and the prouocations of the other. And ſo much for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall originall of apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing is the patrimony of the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlider. <hi>Hee ſhall bee filled with his owne waies.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> No man elſe need worke him any miſchiefe:<note place="margin">Backeſliders patrimony.</note> he will bee ſure to bring ſorrow enough vpon his owne head. <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was here no falſe Prophet, for hee confirmed it afterwards by his owne woefull experience; hee fell to idolatry but for a time, but he wrought himſelfe miſery ſo long as hee liued.<note place="margin">1 Kings 11.14.23.26.</note> Firſt, <hi>Hadad</hi> the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite diſturbes the peaceable gouernment of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> Next, <hi>Rezon</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Eliada</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nebat</hi> lifts vp his hand againſt him. <hi>Aſa</hi> King of <hi>Iudah</hi> to preuent the plots of <hi>Baaſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 16.2 7.12 13.</note> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> commits ſacriledge, robs God and the Kingdome to haue Gold and Siluer to ſend to <hi>Benhadad</hi> the King of <hi>Syria</hi> to relieue him: hee truſts not in God, but truſts in <hi>Benhadad,</hi> God layes a plague vpon him, that <hi>Benhadad</hi> cannot heale, that makes him ſleepe with his fathers, a diſeaſe in his feete. Wee haue ſpoken of Kings, let vs now ſpeake of Kingdomes. The Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> fals to idolatry, they will not come to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> leaſt they ſhould returne to the houſe of <hi>Dauid:</hi> they ſet vp calues in <hi>Dan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.3.</note> in <hi>Bethel. They haue gone a whoring
<pb facs="tcp:7937:11"/>from their God. They ſhall no longer dwell in the Lords land, but they ſhall eate vncleane things in Aſſyria.</hi> They forſooke their God, and the Aſſyrians carry them out of their land. The Iewes <hi>tranſgreſſe after all the abominations of the heathen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 36 14, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and pollute the houſe of the Lord. They deſpiſe Gods Words, and miſuſe his Prophets.</hi> Therefore God deſtroyes their City, and ſends them into <hi>Babylon</hi> to captiuity. They that drinke poyſon may pleaſe their palate but they drinke their owne death. They that goe backe from Gods ſeruice runne forward to their owne ouerthrow. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the conſcience is like duſt in the eye: it makes it foule, it makes it vnſeruiceable, it makes it painefull. The remembrances of backſlidings are like skarres left when wounds are cured; they trouble the owner with the ſight of them. The heathen man knew well the ſtinging force of a troubled conſcience. <hi>The greateſt puniſhment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maxima pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium eſt pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na peccaſſe. Nec illum ſaelus, licet illud fortuna. exoruet muneri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> busſuis, licet tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eatur ac vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot Impunitum eſt, quoniam ſceleris in ſcele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſupplicium eſt <hi>Senec.</hi> epiſt. <hi>97.</hi>
               </note> ſaith hee, <hi>of ſinners, is that they haue ſinned. Neyther is any ſinne vnpuniſhed, although fortune adorne it with rewards, although it defend and maintaine it, becauſe the puniſhment of wickedneſſe is within it ſelfe.</hi> Their greateſt enemy neede wiſh backſliders no greater puniſhments, then their owne waies written in their owne conſciences. Many loſſes and croſſes alſo doe Apoſtatas bring vpon themſelues. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God turnes their wealth vnto pouerty: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee takes away their children, or makes them greater croſſes to them, then if hee tooke them quite away from them, for a croſſe childe is worſe then a loſt childe: the one is a temperary, the other a perpetuall vexation.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> goes backe but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:7937:12"/>way, but the ſword neuer departs from his houſe for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolon</hi> troubles him while hee liues, and grieues him when he dies. <hi>Adoniiah</hi> will bee King in ſpight of him, when his father growes old. Adde vnto this the infamy, that wicked men bring vpon themſelues. Thus <hi>Tamar</hi> foretels <hi>Ammon</hi> of the diſcredit, that would follow vpon his inceſtuous violence, <hi>I whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I cauſe my ſhame to goe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13, 13</note> 
               <hi>and as for thee, thou ſhalt be as one of the fooles in Iſrael.</hi> So men by their folly make themſelues iuſtly a table-talke to others, and their very name to be abhorred. And not their name alone, while they are aliue, but they make their memoriall alſo to ſtinke when themſelues are dead and gone. It is added in Scripture as a perpetuall monument of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> backſliding,<note place="margin">1 Kings 16.29.</note> 
               <hi>Ieroboam the ſonne of Nebat, who made Iſrael to ſinne.</hi> God records the backſlidings of vngodly men in Scripture to the worlds-end,<note place="margin">Math. 10.4.</note> to their perpetuall diſgrace. <hi>Iudas</hi> treaſon is recorded, and he himſelfe not often named without that infamous addition, <hi>Iudas Iſcariot, who alſo betrayed him.</hi> The greateſt Princes whoſe facts no man durſt cenſure while they liued, are by meane Hiſtorians chronicled for all poſterity, and their blemiſhes written with a penne of yron for all the world to peruſe. The proudeſt Popes that haue made Emperours to kiſſe their feete, and turned King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes topſituruy, haue their ſorceries, their ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets; their baſtards vpon recorde to make their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour ſtinke in the eyes of all men.</p>
            <p>Diſgrace then attends vpon defection, and neuer failes it.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>Dead Flies cauſe the oyntment of the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary
<pb facs="tcp:7937:12"/>to ſend forth a ſtinking ſauour: ſo doth a little folly him that is in reputation for wiſdome and honour.</hi> If the booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> be as it is thought to be, <hi>Salomons</hi> recantation after his fall to idolatry; no doubt hee found this dead flye at home, and was a ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his owne precept. The world had not ſuch a paterne, all things conſidered: a man ſo famous for wiſedome fall to ſo foule idolatry as <hi>Salomon</hi> did: the wiſeſt of men ſeduced by a company of fooliſh women. No doubt <hi>Salomon</hi> knew what hee writ, and laboured vnder the loſſe of his owne repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and writ this for a warning to others out of his owne woefull experience.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, defection brings eternall perdition of ſoule and body.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.39.</note> 
               <hi>Wee are not of them who draw backe to perdition, but of them that beleeue to the ſauing of the ſoule.</hi> There are no doubt thouſand thouſands in hell, who are more then filled with their owne waies, and with the remedileſſe, yet inſupportable troubles, that their owne backeſlidings haue brought vpon them. Who if they might liue to vndoe what they haue done, would bee patternes to others to auoyde Apoſtacy. Yet ſo incredulous are wee that liue, that wee neyther beleeue theſe miſeries will come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, though threatned in GODS Word:<note place="margin">Luke 16.31.</note> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would wee repent, if one ſhould ariſe from the dead, that had taſted of thoſe woefull tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>And no wonder if backſliders bring ſo many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries vpon themſelues, when they prouoke ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heauy enemies againſt them. God himſelfe is become their enemy from whoſe ſeruice they are
<pb facs="tcp:7937:13"/>ſlidden. God I ſay,<note place="margin">Deus a quo euerti, cadere in quem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerti, reſurger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in quo mantre, conſiſtere eſt <hi>Aug.</hi> Soli. <hi>c. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>turning from whom is falling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to whom is riſing, tarying in whom is ſtanding,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſoundly informes vs. If there be no ſafety to them that are hated of Kings, within their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, what ſafety can there bee to thoſe whom God hates, in all the world? How can they expect a quiet conſcience, or ſafety in their ſtates, that haue GOD for their aduerſary? Hee will raiſe vp men to bee our enemies if wee be his, and to croſſe vs if we croſſe him. <hi>Salomon</hi> was a wiſe, a rich, and a moſt potent Prince; yet when he forſakes God, GOD rayſeth him vp ſuch enemies, as all <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wiſedome and power could not pull downe. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and his poſterity forſake Gods ſeruice, and ſet vp golden calues in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 15.29.</note> God rayſed vp <hi>Baaſha</hi> to ſmite all the houſe of <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> who leaues him not one breathing. <hi>Baaſha</hi> and his ſonne continue in <hi>Ieroboams</hi> euill cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and GOD ſets againſt him <hi>Zimri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 16.11.</note> who ſlayes all his houſe, with his kinsfolkes and friends, and leaues him not one to piſſe againſt the wall. <hi>Omri</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> his ſonnes for all this take no warning,<note place="margin">2 Kings. 10.1.</note> but adde to the former, other idolatries: God pulls him downe by <hi>Iehu,</hi> who ſlew all his great men and his kinsfolkes, and his Prieſts, vntill he left him none remaining. So hard a thing is it for man to ſtand vpright without ſtanding to God.</p>
            <p>If men be to fauourable, God hath worſer inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to plague vs withall: all the diuels are at his command, and are no other then Gods execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, whom he vſeth in the ſeuerity of his wrath.
<pb facs="tcp:7937:13"/>They will bee ſure to ſtrike home, for they plague vs not for obedience to God, nor for loue of iuſtice, nor yet for gaine or profit, which is the loadſtone of moſt executioners, but for hatred of vs, for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy at our felicity, and ſeeke to bring vs to their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable, and vnpardonable miſery. No doubt, but they will be ſeuere, that ſeeke nothing but the eternall deſtruction of our ſoules and bodies. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all the creatures faile them that faile God. Nay they doe not onely faile them, but exerciſe all their force to hurt and to annoy them. They deny them that ſeruice they were created to do them, and proclaime open warres againſt them, that haue beene openly diſobedient againſt their GOD. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the great King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had enough to doe, and more then he could doe to defend, not his people, but his owne royall perſon from Lice, Frogges, Boyles, Scabbes, Flies, and ſuch like vermine. His ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours could not expell them out of his Country, nor his Guard keepe them out of the bedchamber of their King. There is no mercy to bee found with theſe enemies, they hurt and ſpoyle all where they come. They haue no reaſon, and therefore will bee perſwaded to ſhew no fauour. Thus you ſee what miſeries backſliders bring vpon themſelues: now let vs come to the application.</p>
            <p>The great danger of backſliders, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> 
               <note place="margin">For examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they bring vpon themſelues, driue vs to an exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of our owne condition. We are not igno-what ſeruice we owe to God, let vs ſift our owne ſoules and try how well wee haue performed it.
<pb facs="tcp:7937:14"/>Wee know what profeſſions we haue made in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, let vs ſee how wee haue beene anſwerable to our profeſſions. We ſee, and others haue ſeene how forward wee haue beene in Gods ſeruice, let vs exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our preſent zeale whether it bee correſpondent to the former. If the world haue had a good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vs for equity and charity, let vs take heed that no cauſe bee giuen by vs to diminiſh their good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. In matters of leſſer waight, careleſneſſe is more tolerable; but in things of this conſequence it is not to bee endured. One maine cauſe why many Citizens decay in their eſtates, is becauſe they looke not well to their bookes: they know not what they owe to others: they know not what others owe to them; they are worſe then naught before they bee aware. So is it with euill men, they are gone farre backward, becauſe they daily looke not into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nor obſerue not, how they grow, vpward or downeward. The wounded man is loath to ſearch his wound, the paine makes him vnwilling to diue into it, and ſo it growes vncureable. The backſlider is not willing to ponder vpon his owne courſes, leaſt the beginning of his life condemne the end of it. He goes to hell, becauſe he will not ſee that he is going thither.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">For conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> after examination the concluſion will appeare. If wee find our ſelues acquitted in the iudgement of our owne conſciences from backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding, wee may haue much comfort in our wayes. It is no meane encouragement to goodnes to find ſome progreſſe vpon examination. Hee that plants an Orchyard, takes a ſingular contentment to ſee
<pb facs="tcp:7937:14"/>euery Tree, how it growes and how it beares fruit one yeere more then another. The diligent citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen who in the end of the yeere, when others are idle, caſts vp his owne eſtate, and finds ſome encreaſe of profit ariſing from his trading, his heart is ioyfull within him. Euery mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is his iudge. It muſt conſider of the talents that GOD hath giuen him to trade withall. If it find a good encreaſe, it giues him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation within, that God will one day giue him before men and Angells. <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſeruant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math, 25.21.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt beene faithfull ouer a few things, I will make thee ruler ouer much: enter thou in to the ioy of thy Lord.</hi> Such a man may call in his friends and neighbours to reioyce with him,<note place="margin">Luke 15.8.9.</note> as the Woman did, who had found her peece of ſiluer that was loſt. When <hi>Philip</hi> had beene called by Chriſt, how triumphantly doth hee boaſt to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel, Wee haue found him of whom Moſes in the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.45.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prophets did write, Ieſus of Nazareth the Sonne of Ioſeph.</hi> So may hee triumph who vpon iuſt examination finds, that hee hath made ſome good progreſſe in the wayes of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> comfort muſt bee ſeconded with care,<note place="margin">For caution.</note> els will it end in diſcomfort. Wee had need to bee cautious that we may ſtand it out for time to come. Wee muſt not bee lifted vp, that wee haue ſtood it out ſo long, but be watchfull, that wee may hold out vnto the end. Hee that hath eſcaped one great ſtorme at Sea, muſt not be ſecure though, till hee come vnto the hauen. Another ſtorme may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger him that hath eſcaped a former. Many are
<pb facs="tcp:7937:15"/>the prouocations of the world. If it preuaile not one way, it will try another. If the aduerſityes of the world will not diſcourage vs, it will try, whither the pleaſures or profits of it will worke vs. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes vs carefully to take heed of all theſe but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to bee wary, that while wee are buſy with the world abroad, wee bee not betryed by our owne fleſh within. In a beſieged Citty it is not vnuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, while the beſiged reſiſt an aſſault made at one ſide of the Towne for ſome falſe traitour to let in the enemy on the other ſide and toruine the Citty. So while wee thinke our ſelues ſafe againſt the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of the world, wee are often betrayed by the corruption of our owne fleſh. They are fooles that worke themſelues troubles: yet whence come all our troubles, but from our owne backeſlidings, and whence come our defections, but from our careleſneſſe? Wee haue a vigilant enemy, who neglects no occaſion of aduantage, let vs bee as watchfull for our owne preſeruation, leaſt God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prouoked by our negligence giue vs ouer to our ſpirituall enemy to bee ruined. A breach is not healed at that coſt it might bee preuented. Though there may be a recouery, yet ſome skarres of infamy and infirmity will be remaining.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> it ſounds terrour to them that after examination are forced to ſet downe for the ſumme of their accounts, <note place="margin">For conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> That they are backſliders. Their owne waies will be their owne ouerthrow: there is no neede of great Politicians to ouer reach them with ſome ſubtill deuiſe to the ouerthrow of their honours, liues, or eſtates: they themſelues will lay
<pb facs="tcp:7937:15"/>ſnares for themſelues, and digge pitts with their own wickednes to bury their fortunes in, with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. There needs no great and mighty men whoſe hatred and power may bring downe backeſliders, they fal with their owne waight. We haue corrupted our ſelues internally by our defection, and internall corruption workes externall deſtruction. A rotten Apple needs not bee cruſhed, the inward putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will bring it to nothing though no hand touch it. A wounded body needs no Sword to kill it, nor no poiſon to deſtroy it, it hath that within, that will bring it to the graue. A decayed Houſe needs not bee pulled downe by the hands of worke-men, it will fall of it ſelfe for want of reparation. An high Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ouergrowne in terme and territories, needs no outward foes to put an end to it. Ciuill warres and home bred vexations ſetled in the veines of it, will lay it low enough. So is it with Apoſtataes. There needs no forraine art, nor force to vndoe them, they daily further their finall ouerthrow. How euer it goe with them in this world, their owne conſciences can tell them, it will neuer goe well with them in the world to come. <hi>Goe to now, yee back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders, weepe and houle for the miſeries, that ſhall come vpon you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 5.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> finding our ſelues in ſo ill a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; let vs betimes recall our ſelues.<note place="margin">For reuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> It is not good to ride too farre out of the way. It will aske the more labour to come in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Wee doe not terrify men with their euill conditions to vexe them, but to draw them out of it.
<pb facs="tcp:7937:16"/>Let vs conſider from whom wee are ſlidden: it is from GOD, to whom if wee doe not returne, wee can neuer expect ſafety in any other. Hee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs for fayling him: others cannot ſaue vs for cleauing to them. It is ſufficient that others ſeeke our ouerthrow, let vs not ſeeke our owne. While we liue in this world, we haue liberty to returne to God, and opportunity to ſeeke the Kingdome of God. But if we ſlide away more and more from God in this world, we can haue no acceſſe to God in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world. The traueller that knowes he is out of the way, needes no great perſwaſions to goe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The ſicke man that knowes his diſeaſe to be dangerous, wants not many arguments to vrge him to bee ſtudious of his owne recouery. If wee were as ſenſible of ſpirituall errours and diſeaſes, as wee are of temporall, ſmall Rhetoricke would ſerue to draw vs backe from our backſlidings. Our eſtate is naught now, but it is like to be much worſe hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and which is no ſmall addition to our miſery, we know not how ſoone we ſhall bee moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: there may bee but a minute betweene vs and death; there cannot bee aboue a minute more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene death and hell. How long then will you runne on toward your owne damnation? Returne, returne to Gods fauour, leaſt yee periſh in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Remember whence yee are fallen and repent before the candleſticke of your life be remoued, and ye left in perpetuall darkneſſe.<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> it is not ſufficient for vs to recall our ſelues,<note place="margin">For reclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> but a needfull deede of charity when wee haue recalled our ſelues, to reclaime others. At leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:7937:16"/>to endeauour to reclaime them, for the ſucceſſe is to be expected from God. Wee ſee the danger of defection: they ſee it not: the ſight of it makes vs to returne to God, let vs ſtriue to make others to ſee their miſery too that they alſo may returne from their backſlidings. They that haue beene cured of the Goute or Stone are no niggards of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but eaſily communicate the ſame vnto others. It is our bleſſed Sauiours command to S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.32.</note> that when he ſhould finde himſelfe conuerted, hee ſhould ſtrengthen his brethren. It is <hi>Dauids</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Reſtore vnto mee the ioy of thy ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 51.12.13</note> 
               <hi>and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me with thy free ſpirit. Then will I teach tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours thy way, and ſinners ſhall bee conuerted vnto thee.</hi> Chriſtianity teacheth vs to liue in a communion of ſpirituall and temporall comforts and counſailes. Which communion requires not onely that we be liberall to them that want bodily meanes, but alſo to aduiſe for the beſt ſuch as want ſpirituall directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If wee haue erred and recalled our ſelues, let vs not thinke all the worke done. Wee are a Body: the hand hath not done his owne part in pulling a thorne out of it ſelfe. it muſt pull it out of the foote alſo. Heauen is not prepared for vs alone, we muſt endeauour to leade others thither with vs.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the firſt part of the Text, the portion of backſliders. The portion of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient children followes in the concluſion of the Text.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:7937:17"/> And a good man <hi>ſhall be ſatisfied</hi> from <hi>thoſe things</hi> that <hi>are</hi> within himſelfe.</q>
            <p>Good men haue matter enough within their owne ſoules to giue ſatisfaction to themſelues in the greateſt dangers that can befall them. Hence come thoſe admirable boaſtings of Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſalme 16.8.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſet the Lord alwaies before mee: becauſe he is at my right hand, I ſhall not be moued.</hi> Though his owne ſtrength might faile him, yet he knew God, could not. <hi>The Lord is my light and my ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme. 27.1.</note> 
               <hi>whom ſhall I feare? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I bee afraid?</hi> His owne ſtore might faile him in a famine, though he had a kingdome: his own art might diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt him, though he were wiſer then his enemies, if the peſtilence came. As the ſilly ſheepe then thinkes himſelfe ſafe vnder the ſhepheards pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, when the wolfe layes for him, ſo doth hee vnder Gods, in greateſt perils. <hi>The Lord is my Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, I ſhall not want.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 23.1.4</note> 
               <hi>Yea though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare no euill, for thou art with me, thy rod and thy ſtaffe, they comfort me.</hi> And leaſt it might be thought to be his caſe alone, hee ioynes others with him that feare God.<note place="margin">Pſam 46.1, 2, 3</note> 
               <hi>God is our refuge and ſtrength: a very preſent helpe in trouble. Therefore will wee not feare though the Earth bee remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and though the Mountaines bee caryed into the midſt of the Sea. Though the waters thereof roare and bee troubled, though the Mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof. Selah.</hi> A very high ſtraine indeed, and worthy of a Muſicall note of Eleuation. Hence come S. <hi>Pauls</hi> triumphes. He knew hee
<pb facs="tcp:7937:17"/>had enough within him to vphold him, what euer outwardly happened in the world. <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8 38.39.</note> 
               <hi>nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord.</hi> An Apoſtolicall height! yet ſuch a pitch as may bee attayned by priuate Chriſtians, whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> ioynes with himſelfe in the body of this triumph. Many are the gifts and graces that God hath enriched a good mans ſoule withall. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe many, diuers there are that are giuen him to giue ſatisfaction to his owne ſoule, though I deny not, but ſundry other internall indowments are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him to enable him to honor God, and to do good to men by his actions, while the earth affords him a dwelling place, and till heauen be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him. God deales with him as a father with his tender child, whom he beſtowes great breeding vpon to his no little coſt, partly to make his life profitable to others, and partly to make it comfortable to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Thus God furniſhes his Children with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of graces, that they themſelues may haue cauſe to bleſſe God for ſuch as giue ſatisfaction to their owne ſoules; and others, for ſuch as bring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and benefit to them. Let vs now view the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and bring into a liſt ſuch graces as ſhine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and enable Gods ſeruant to ſatisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">Meanes of ſelfe ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> The firſt iewell that God beſtowes vpon the ſoule of a good man, is peace of conſcience. I put it in the firſt place, becauſe it yeelds moſt comfort.<note place="margin">Peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</note> This can ſatisfie a man inwardly whatſoeuer befals him
<pb facs="tcp:7937:18"/>outwardly in the world. His conſcience being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vnſetled hath led him through all the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that euery man paſſed through in this world. Hee lookes backe to the ſtate of Creation. Hee viewes it as a ſtate of innocency, and a condition of felicity. But (ſaith the conſcience) what is that to thee? <hi>Adam</hi> was innocent and happy: but by his fall hee hath made thee ſinfull and miſerable. There is as little comfort in thinking of loſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, as in a ſtaruing man ruminating vpon his loſt Gold and periſhing. It doubles the greefe in our ſelues to thinke wee haue beene happy in our firſt parents. Seeking reſt in the ſtate of Creation and finding none, at length his thoughts faſten vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eſtate of corruption. The former was a good, but is a loſt condition. The latter is a bad one, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loſt then found, yet eaſily found but not eaſily loſt. This is his naturall condition. This makes him hang downe his head with heauineſſe. At length a third condition offers it ſelfe vnto his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, a ſtate of reconciliation to GOD by the blood of Chriſt. His conſcience cannot deny hee hath ſinned, but God in the Goſpell offers him pardon for all his ſinnes in Chriſt. This Offer hee hath applyed to himſelfe by a true faith. Now the plaiſter applyed hath healed the wound. His tranſgreſſions are remoued from him,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 103.12</note> 
               <hi>as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt.</hi> His conſcience now is at peace within him. His ſoule is ioyfull. It is ſecured from the wrath of GOD: what need it feare the wrath of men? Hee finds peace from Heauen: hee feares not warres on Earth.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.3.</note> Thus <hi>being iuſtified by
<pb facs="tcp:7937:18"/>faith hee hath peace with GOD through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And this peace makes him to <hi>glory in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 91.1.5.6</note> Now doth he <hi>dwell in the ſecret place of the moſt high,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſhall abide vnder the ſhadow of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi> Now plagues and dangers are not ſo terrible to him as before, becauſe he knowes none can hurt him whom God loues and protects. A ſhip at Sea playes it the midſt of ſtormes, there are no trees to ſhelter it, no anchores can hold it. Nothing cannot can ſecure it that is without it; all the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it hath is from within. If it be well ballanced it may eſcape. So is it with the ſhippe of mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. When GODS wrath ſmites vpon it like a ſtorme, and the world blowes vpon it like a tempeſt, no honours can quiet it, no tiches can pacifie it. If any thing keepe it from ſinking, it muſt bee the inward peace of a good conſcience: this aſſures him of Gods loue, and that giues him ſatisfaction. The ſoule was made according to Gods Image: nothing then can ſatisfie it, but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; according to whoſe Image it was created. Take a ſeale and ioyne it to waxe, the ſtampe or image that is left in the waxe, cannot be filled but with the ſame ſeale againe. Neyther can Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in man be fully ſatisfied but by the fruition of God himſelfe. <hi>Mans nature,</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) <hi>although it be mutable, yet it may obtaine bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by cleauing vnto the higheſt God, who is the onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable good. To make it happy, it muſt haue ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for all the defects of it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ciu. Dei lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Now all the world is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſatisfie the neceſſities of the ſoule, God onely can doe it.</hi> The ſame Father in his Confeſſions, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:7937:19"/>the end of mans creation, to ſhew what onely can giue him ſatisfaction. <hi>Thou haſt made vs</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Feciſti nos ad te; et inquietu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cor noſtrum donec requieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat in te. Aug. Coufeſſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for thee, and our heart is reſtleſſe, till it reſt in thee.</hi> This was <hi>Cyprians</hi> counſell to <hi>Donatus</hi> to ſeeke for ſatisfaction not from the world without him, but from his owne conſcience within him. <hi>There is but one pleaſing and ſure tranquility: one ſolid, firme, and perpetuall ſecurity, if a man withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the tempeſts of this diſquieting world being ſurely ſetled in a ſafe hauen, and lift vp his eyes from earth to heauen, and being admitted to Gods fauour, and in his mind now neereſt to his God, glories to find within his owne conſcience whatſoeuer others deeme high or great among worldly commodities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nihil appetere tam, nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderare de ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo poteſt, qui ſaeculo maior eſt. Cypr. ep. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He can now couet nothing, he needs deſire nothing of the world, who is already greater then the world.</hi> Now as he need deſire nothing that the world hath, who is at peace with God, ſo need he feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that the world can doe againſt him, for God can ſupply him with what the world denies him, and can protect him againſt what the world threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens him with. Thus is hee by Gods fauour in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of all the world able to giue ſatisfaction to himſelfe. The legacy that our Sauiour left vnto his Diſciples was peace.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. 14.27.</hi> Non pax tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris quia expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendierant mul tis tributationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed pax pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoris et paxaeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis prima in praeſenti, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda infuturo. Lud. vita. Chriſti part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>77.</hi> fig. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peace I leaue with you, my peace I giue vnto you.</hi> What that peace was, let <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus</hi> declare, <hi>Not peaceable times in this life, but a peaceable heart leading to eternall life.</hi> As when the mind is troubled with the ſenſe of Gods anger, all the world cannot pacifie it: gold and ſiluer pleaſe no more then ſtrawes: friends are but miſerable comforters: we languiſh inwardly notwithſtanding a world of outward comforts: ſo when the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:7937:19"/>is pacified with the ſweete perſwaſion of Gods fauour, all the tribulations of the world cannot daunt that heart, but like the Bee it can come abroad and taſte the commodities of ſummer, and feede it ſelfe with the honey it hath gathered biding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hiue, when the winter ſtormes with her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts. By this meanes hee enioyes the benefits of all outward comforts, and can fuſtaine himſelfe with his inward peace in the midſt of all outward croſſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond fauour wherewith God graces a good mans ſoule to enable him to ſatisfie himſelfe is the teſtimony of Gods Spirit. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">Teſtimony of Gods Spirit.</note> This confirmes and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures vs of the former peace with God. It breeds alſo vnſpeakeable ioy in the apprehenſion of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. That <hi>reioycing</hi> we haue <hi>in tribulations in hope of the glory of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.3.5.</note> proceede from <hi>the holy Ghoſt which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs.</hi> The ſumme of the teſtimony of Gods ſpirit within vs is to perſwade vs fully of Gods loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to vs in Chriſt. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> inſtructs vs. It is <hi>the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.16</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit it ſelfe beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God.</hi> Now what better newes can the Spirit of God bring to vs, then the tidings of Gods fauour. <hi>Dauid</hi> preferres it before his being.<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thy louing kindnes is better then life.</hi> This teſtimony internall of Gods fauour to the ſoule is able to ſuſtaine a man againſt all outward force and malice. They that haue ſtore of foode and rayment, of weapons, of munition, being lodged in a ſtrong hold, feare not the enemy without, though he be very powerfull. No more need a good man feare troubles. Hee that
<pb facs="tcp:7937:20"/>hath ſtore of gold and ſiluer within his coffers, cares not though he want braſſe or leaden mony. So hee that is warranted by Gods Spirit, that God affects him, neede not care much though he want health, or wealth, or other worldly comforts. Thus Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dwelling in him, makes him able to ſatisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, howeuer it goe with others.</p>
            <p>A third bleſſing that helpes the ſeruant of God, to vphold himſelfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <note place="margin">Memory.</note> is his memory. This is the cheſt of the ſoule, wherein ſhe lookes vp all her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. It is the retentiue faculty of the mind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the inſtructions it hath formerly read or heard, are regiſtred. The vnderſtanding without this is like a prodigall, it receiues many rents, but ſpends all. Or like the weake ſtomacke that takes food, but is not nouriſhed by it, becauſe it cannot hold it to feede vpon it. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> compares the memory to a barne, wherein things ſeene are laid vp for future prouiſion. <hi>Thou ſeeſt ſomething</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>and perceiueſt it with thine eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in euang. Ioh. Tract. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and commendeſt it to thy memory: and that which thou haſt committed to thy memory is there laid vp within in a ſecret place, as it were in a barne: as it were in a treaſury: as it were in a certaine cloſet, or inward garden.</hi> The memory then is much beneficiall to the ſettling and ſatisfying of a good mans minde: meanes of further comfort may be kept from him. The Scriptures and creatures may be denyed to his eyes: ſermons and friends maybe kept from his eares: but what is lodged in his memory, can neuer be taken from him by the malice of perſecutors: there may he read in the darkeſt dungeon, without a candle. Two things there are that may ſtagger the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb facs="tcp:7937:20"/>of a good man in time of trouble. The one is the doubting of Gods power to deliuer him, in regard of the greatneſſe of his afflictions. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the queſtioning of Gods will, becauſe of the greatneſſe of his ſinnes. The memory helpes to giue ſatisfaction to both theſe doubts. To the firſt, it anſweres by precedents.<note place="margin">Memoria animae noſtrae quaſi columna eſt; notae huic in ſcriptae, bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum exempla. Greg. Nyſſ. Tract. <hi>2.</hi> in</note> 
               <hi>The memory</hi> (according to <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi>) <hi>is the pillar of the ſoule: the memorials written in it, are the examples of good men.</hi> So the godly Iewes perſwade themſelues, that God can doe wonders for them, becauſe hee hath done them for their fathers. <hi>O God,</hi> ſay they, <hi>wee haue heard with our eares, and our fathers haue told vs, what workes thou didſt in their daies, in the time of old.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. cap.</hi> 4. Pſalme 44.1.2</note> 
               <hi>How thou didſt driue out the heathen with thy hand and plantedſt them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme. 119.58</note> 
               <hi>how thou didſt afflict the people and caſt them out.</hi> So <hi>Dauid</hi> cheares vp himſelfe, and rouzes vp his ſpirits, <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred thy iudgements of old, O Lord, and haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted my ſelfe.</hi> Thus the good mans memory tells him, what God hath done for others, and his reaſon informes him, that he can doe as much for him. If he ſhould be tempted to doubt of what God hath done for others, yet he cannot doubt of ſuch great acts as God hath done for himſelfe. Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> armes himſelfe againſt the Gyant, <hi>The Lord that hath deliuered me out of the pawe of the Lyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.37</note> 
               <hi>and out of the pawe of the Beare, hee will deliuer mee out of the hand of this Philiſtine.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrengthens himſelfe from his <hi>Aſian</hi> deliuerance,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.10</note> 
               <hi>God deliuered vs from ſo great a death, and doth deliuer vs, in whom we truſt, that hee will yet deliuer vs.</hi> Thus he perſwades himſelfe ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Gods power to free him from other inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences
<pb facs="tcp:7937:21"/>by reaſon of his Romane deliuerance. <hi>I was deliuered out of the mouth of the Lyon. And the Lord will deliuer me from euery euill worke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.17.18</note> 
               <hi>and will preſerue me vnto his heauenly Kngdome.</hi> So the goodmans me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory aſſiſts him againſt all doubting of GODS power. To the ſecond doubt it anſwers by promiſes. Gods will is knowne by his Word. What hee hath promiſed to doe that he will do. Thus the memory lodging Gods ſeuerall promiſes of ſpirituall and temporall comforts in the cloſet of the ſoule, leaues no occaſion to doubt Gods will. This makes <hi>Dauid</hi> in his ſorrows put God in minde of his promiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God neuer forget it. This comforts him in his greateſt ſorrows, that God hath promiſed him deliuerance.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49.50</note> 
               <hi>Remember the word vnto thy ſeruant, vpon which thou haſt cauſed mee to hope. This is my comfort in my affliction: for thy word hath quickened me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth meanes to ſettle the godly mans qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of mind is contentation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> a gift that God hath giuen him,<note place="margin">Contentation.</note> whereby he can ſatisfie himſelfe in any condition. This attends vpon godlines, as the ſhadow waites vpon the ſhining ſunne. For this we haue S. <hi>Pauls</hi> warrant, <hi>Godlines with contentment, is great gaine,</hi> or rather,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.6</note> 
               <hi>with it's ſelfe ſufficiency.</hi> For S. <hi>Pauls</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was not to informe vs, that godlines was great gaine, if a man could get contentednes ioyned with it, but rather to ſhew vs, that godlines brings ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of it ſelfe to giue ſatisfaction to the godly man, although he want many outward comforts. Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes then brings contentednes with it, or at leaſt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to giue contentment, if her ſtore be well viewed: for ſo much the Greeke word imports.<note place="margin">Sufficientia ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The <hi>Syriacke</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7937:21"/>tranſlation confirms this interpretation, which giues this briefe paraphraſe of the words. <hi>For our gaine is great, which is the feare of God, with the vſe of our ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum vſu ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientiae noſtrae.</note> As much as to ſay, Godlines brings enough with it to ſatisfie vs, if we know how to vſe that ſtore it hath attending vpon it, &amp; beſtows vpon vs. This made <hi>Dauid</hi> prefer the righteous mans pouerty before the wicked mans plenty. <hi>A little that the righteous man hath, is better then the riches of many wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 37.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man is contented with a little: the wicked man is not ſatisfied with abundance. This reaſon may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from <hi>Salomon, Dauids</hi> vnderſtanding ſon,<note place="margin">Prou. 15.16</note> 
               <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is little with the feare of the Lord, then great treaſure and trouble there with.</hi> A good man is ſatisfied with a little, for he enioyes it with quietnes of mind. A wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man is not ſatisfied with a great deale, becauſe he hath many cares and troubles with it. A good man is content with little on earth, becauſe he lookes for abundance: in heauen. A wicked man is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with abundance here, becauſe he lookes for little hereafter. Religion may well bring ſatisfaction to a good man, becauſe it brings him to God the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodnes.<note place="margin">Pſalme 16.5.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is the portion of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. God perſwads <hi>Abraham</hi> to take care for nothing but to walke before him in vprightnes: and addes this, <hi>I am the Lord al-ſufficient:</hi> that is, I haue ſufficient, I will prouide for thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Shaddac. aſher lo dac. cui eſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientia.</note> care thou onely for my ſeruice. Piety then that brings a man to haue an intreſt in God, ſhewes him that what is wanting in him ſhall be ſupplyed by God, who hath enough to ſupply the wants of all the creatures. Now he that will not be content with God himſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:7937:22"/>how ſhould he be ſatisfied if hee had all the world, all the ſtore whereof falls infinitely ſhort of Gods? So then when the whole world cannot giue ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to a couetous man, a little contents a good man: becauſe he knowes hee hath enough in God. Though another man hath more knowledge then he, yet is he contented, becauſe God hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated enough to him to make him know Chriſt and the way to the Kingdome of Heauen. Though many haue more wealth, yet hee reſts ſatisfied with leſſe, conſidering that hee hath Gods fauour with it, which many of them want. Hee wiſely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts the conueniences that attend vpon his ſmaller portion, and the inconueniences that accompany their greater poſſeſſions. They haue many cares that cannot be auoyded, for many croſſes and loſſes accompany great and rich imployments. He is freed from thoſe cares to ſerue God quietly with a little. They are ſubiect to many diſorders: he wants fuell to maintayne the fire of luſt. They haue a great account to giue vnto God, at the day of iudgement of the imployment of their ten talents: hee hath a lighter reckoning for his fiue. Theſe thoughts giue him contentation, and contentation giues him ſelfe-ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The fift gift of God that furthers this ſelfe-ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in a good man, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <note place="margin">Temperance.</note> is Temperance. Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues that adorne the ſoule of man, this is none of the leaſt. And it is much materiall to ſelfe-ſatisfaction: for nature is contented with a little, and temperance teacheth a man to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from ſuperfluities, and content himſelfe with
<pb facs="tcp:7937:22"/>that that nature can bee content withall. S. <hi>Paul</hi> had well learned this leſſon,<note place="margin">philip. 4.11.12</note> 
               <hi>I haue learned in what ſoeuer ſtate I am, therewith to bee content. I know both how to bee abaſed, and I know how to abound: euery where and in all things I am inſtructed, both to bee full and to bee hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need.</hi> The goodman remembers the world is but an Inne: hee muſt bee temperate, that his mony may hold out to his iournyes end. Hee ſhall exceed when he comes home. Thus his frugality and temperance giues him ſome ſatiſfaction, becauſe it makes that content him which will not ſatiſfie an intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate appetite. This makes him not greedy of worldly wealth, becauſe a little will ſerue his turne. Hee ſtriues to bee as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith hee ſhould be, <hi>It becomes not a Chriſtian</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to gape greedily after this worlds gaine, to whom a Kingdome is promiſed in Heauen: but by abſtinence to liue as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the ſeruant of ſuch a Lord</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. <hi>248.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that he may liue in ioy with his Lord for euer.</hi> This temperance is increaſed in Gods Seruant by conſideration of the fleeting of all worldly comforts, and the durablenes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall treaſures, which makes him the more ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the vſe of the one, and more plentifull in exerciſing the other. This<note n="b" place="margin">Illa diues eſt, quae in Deo diues eſt, illa locuples eſt quae locuples in Christo eſt: bona illa ſunt, quae ſunt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualia, diuina, caeleſtia, quae nos ad Deum ducant quae nobiſcum apud Deum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petua poſſeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne permane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Caeterum quaecum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ unt in ſeculo accepta, et hic cum ſeculo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſura tam contemni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent; quam mundus ipſe contemnitur, cuius pompis et delicijs iam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciauimus. Cypr. de diſc. et hab. virg.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> very well knew, and that made him to vſe thſe arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade virgins to moderation in their apparell: <hi>Shee is rich</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that is rich in God: Shee is wealthy that is wealthy in Chriſt: thoſe are true riches which are ſpirituall, Diuine, and heauenly, which lead vs to God, which remaine with vs in perpetual poſſeſſion in the preſence of God. But whatſoeuer earthly things we haue receiued
<pb facs="tcp:7937:23"/>in the world, and muſt leaue here with the world muſt as eaſily be contemned as the world it ſelfe is contemned, whoſe pompes and delights we haue already renounced.</hi> This temperance when Gods ſeruant hath by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſettled in himſelfe, it equals his minde to his meanes when it cannot bring his meanes to his mind. It makes him well contented with what he hath, when he cannot haue what hee rather would haue.<note place="margin">De laelitia et triſtitianaſcitur temperantia, cuius est tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia cauſae. laelitia fructus, Temperata laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nihil aliud quam tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia est Ber. par. et var. ſerm. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Bernard</hi> informes vs, That <hi>temperance is bred of cheerefulneſſe and heauineſſe; the cauſe of it is heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the fruit is cheerefulneſſe. So that Temperance is nothing elſe but a well tempered cheerefulneſſe.</hi> The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mans temperance purgeth his heart, and ſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth him the right and moderate vſe of all Gods creatures in his body. So that as a good ſtomacke turnes the hardeſt meate into nouriſhment, whereas a weake one turnes the choyſe of meates into diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo the temperate heart feedes the body with the hardeſt eſtate, whereas the intemperate man ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines his ſoule and body with his wealth. <hi>Bernard</hi> on that place in the 90. Pſalme, Thou ſhalt treade vpon the Aſpe and the Baſiliske, and ſhalt trample vnder feete the Lyon and the Dragon gloſſes thus. <hi>The Lyon will roare, who will not be afraid? If there ſhall be found any ſuch, he ſhall be ſtiled a valiant man. But when the Lyon is fruſtrate of his purpoſe, there is a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon hidden in the ſand, that by his poyſoned breath he may taint the ſoule, breathing into it, as it were, the concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of earthly things. Who, thinkeſt thou, ſhalt eſcape his deceits? no man ſurely, but a wiſe man.</hi> But peraduenture while thou art afraid <hi>to come downe to theſe lures, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body vrges thee with trouble, and loe forthwith the Aſpe
<pb facs="tcp:7937:23"/>is preſent. For he thinkes he hath gotten a conuenient time for himſelfe. Who will not be exaſperated by this Ape?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quis non exaſ. perabitur ab aſpide iſta.</note> 
               <hi>Surely the temperate and moderate man, who knowes how to abound and how to ſuffer penury. I ſuppoſe that vpon this occaſion, the ill flattering wicked eye will endeauour to bewitch thee. Who will turne away his eye? Truely the iuſt man will, who not onely will not himſelfe take the glory which is Gods, but will not ſo much as receiue it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in pſ. <hi>90</hi> ſer. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>when it is offred him by another.</hi> The temperate man then auoyds all theſe different ſnares, and ſo giues ſatisfaction to himſelfe. I will conclude this meanes with S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> exclamation, and commendation of temperance.<note place="margin">O magna et admirabilis abſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntiae vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, per quam non ſolum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum ſalus, agitur, ſed etiam corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſanitaspoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidetur. <hi>Aug.</hi> ad frat. in ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Ser <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O great and admirable vertue of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, wherby not onely the ſafety of the ſoule is preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but alſo the health of the body is poſſeſſed.</hi> And what can a man require more to bee able to giue ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himſelfe then ſafety of ſoule with health of body?</p>
            <p>The ſixt meanes whereby a good man is ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to giue ſatisfaction to himſelfe, is Patience. It is a companion of Godlineſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> It is a way whereby the ſeruants of GOD turne away many troubles from themſelues,<note place="margin">Patience.</note> which foole-hardy men bring vpon themſelues by their peeuiſh haſtineſſe. <hi>The firmenes of patience,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, is a ſtaffe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. ſent.</note> 
               <hi>whereby the rage of Wolues is kept off.</hi> Yet let the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of GOD be as patient as he can, hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not turne away all troubles from himſelfe. Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therefore ſtands him in good ſteade alſo when troubles are come vpon him. It makes him owner of his owne ſoule.<note place="margin">Luke 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>In your patience poſſeſſe yee your ſoules,</hi> fayth our bleſſed Sauiour. Vpon which words
<pb facs="tcp:7937:24"/>of his,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ustos omnium virlutum pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia eſt, in qua animas, quae cor pus poſſident, peſ ſidemus, cum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſas animas ad patiendum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione regimus. Vnde <hi>Beda:</hi> Sic conditi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliter ſumus, vt, ratio ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, et anima poſſideat corpus. Ius verò animae a corporis poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione praepeditur ſi non priûs ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma aratione poſſidetur. <hi>Lud.</hi> de vit. Chriſti. part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi> not. <hi>9, 10</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ludolphus</hi> thus dilates, <hi>Patience is the keeper of all vertues, by which we doe poſſeſſe our ſoules, which doe poſſeſſe our bodies when wee doe by reaſon diſpoſe our owne ſoules to ſuffering. But he that is impatient, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth not his owne ſoule becauſe he cannot reſtraine the fury and anger of his owne heart.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Bede</hi> ſayth, <hi>We are ſo wonderfully framed, that reaſon ought to poſſeſſe the ſoule, and the ſoule the body. But the right of the ſoule is hindred from the poſſeſſion of the body, if the ſoule be not firſt poſſeſſed by reaſon. The Lord therefore hath ſhewed vs, that patience is the keeper of our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it hath taught vs, how to poſſeſſe our owne ſelues.</hi> Thoſe things then which are troubleſome to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, are not ſo to a good man, becauſe his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence makes heauy burdens, light. To this end hee conſiders of many things to make him patient. He ruminates vpon the originall of all afflictions, and remembers that they come from heauen. Hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures them patiently, becauſe he would be loth to be found a fighter againſt God. Hee reſolues with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>I will be dumbe, and not open my mouth, becauſe thou diddeſt it O Lord.</hi> He proceeds in his meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the progreſſe of all troubles:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme 32.6.</hi> Oportet paetien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ferri, quod non poteſt feſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter auferri. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Temp. Ser. <hi>223.</hi> Vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> es mihi Domine Ieſu, et ſpeculum patiendi, et prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nium patien. eis. Trabe me poſt te, libenter te ſequor, liben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fruor.</note> remembers that they are called <hi>waters,</hi> and therefore will haue their tide, neither will they ebbe, till they haue done flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He agrees with <hi>Auguſtine, that we ought to beare that with patience, which cannot be taken away in haſte.</hi> He lookes backe to the moſt famous patterne of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that euer mans eyes beheld in man, and cryes out with <hi>Bernard, Thou art to mee, O Lord IESVS, both a mirrour of patience, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, when I am patient. Draw me after thee, I will
<pb facs="tcp:7937:24"/>follow thee willingly, and enioy thee more willingly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Si ſic bonus er Domine ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious te, qualis futurus es aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentibus te? <hi>Ber.</hi> in Cant. Ser. <hi>47.</hi> Paena, de ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſis mundi ille ſenit, cuiet laetitia et gloriae omnis in mundo eſt. Ille maeree et deflet, ſi ſibi malè ſit in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, cui bene non poteſt eſſe poſt ſeculum. Caeterùm nullus ijs dolor eſt de incurſatione ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum praeſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quibus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducia eſt futuro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum bonrum. Cypr. ad. Demetr <hi>ſ. 15. Rom. 8.18. 2. Cor. 4.17.</hi> Epict. Ench. <hi>c. 79.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O Lord if thou be thus good vnto them that follow thee, how good wilt thou be vnto them that ouertake thee?</hi> Hee lookes forward to the heauenly end of all worldly troubles, and concludes with <hi>Cyprian, He feeles it a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to be croſſed in the world all whoſe ioy and glory is in the world. He mornes and laments, that it goes ill with him in this life, with whom it cannot goe well after this life. But they greeue not for the inuaſion of preſent euills, that haue a confident expectation of future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth his <hi>Romanes, I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the glory, which ſhall be reuealed in vs.</hi> Thus hee inſtructeth his <hi>Corinthians, Our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for vs a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory.</hi> So then our good man collects that farre more certainely from Scripture, which the heathen man collected from nature, <hi>Tyrants may kill me indeed, but they cannot hurt me.</hi> Hee ſees that temporall euills may ſtand with his eternall good. Yea hee ſees they are not euill in themſelues ſimply, but rather in mens eſtimation. So could the naturall, or rather morall <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſay, <hi>Men are troubled not with the things that befall them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">On ta pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, alla ta perton pragmaton dog. mata. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but with thoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which they haue of the things. For example. Death is not euill, els would it haue appeared ſo to Socrates al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: but our opinion of death is that which makes it euill.</hi> Hence it is that a good man endures ſicknes and death quietly which much perplexeth a wicked man. So <hi>Cyprian</hi> labours to perſwade the Gentiles that croſſes appeared far otherwiſe to the Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:7937:25"/>then to them; becauſe there was an infinite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the bearing of them, <hi>Thinke ye that we beare aduerſity equally with you, when ye ſee that the ſame croſſes are not borne alike by vs and you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ypr. ad Demet. ſ. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Thus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience furthers ſelfe-ſatiſfaction by turning away many croſſes and making others eaſier to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth helpe that a good man hath to helpe to ſatiſfy himſelfe withall, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <note place="margin">Innocency.</note> is his innocency, which though it be not compleat in action, yet it is in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. And it is a great comfort in all croſſes. A good man is oftentimes croſſed by them, of whom hee hath deſerued no hurt but rather much good. Hence ariſeth a world of inward comfort in outward croſſes. Heerewith <hi>Dauid</hi> comforts himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord againſt the ſlanders inuented by <hi>Sauls</hi> followers, beleeued by <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe, and very coſtly to <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 7.3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord my God,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>if I haue done this, if there be any iniquity in my hands; If I haue rewarded euill vnto him that was at peace with me: (yea I haue deliuered him that without cauſe is mine enemy.) Let the enemy perſecute my ſoule, and take it, yea, let him tread downe my life vpon the Earth, and lay mine honour in the duſt:</hi> Heerewith <hi>Iob</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts himſelfe againſt the vnkindneſſe of his friends, <hi>GOD forbid that I ſhould iuſtify you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 27.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>till I dye I will not remoue my integrity from me. My righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I hold faſt and will not let it goe: my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I liue.</hi> And elſe where,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.35.36.37.</note> If <hi>mine aduerſary had written a Booke, Surely I would take it vpon my ſhoulder, and binde it as a Crowne to mee. I would declare vnto him the
<pb facs="tcp:7937:25"/>number of my ſteps, as a Prince would I goe neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him</hi> Yea in ſickneſſes and afflictions that come from God, innocency is a great comfort, witneſſe <hi>Hezekias</hi> prayer in his great ſickneſſe neere vnto death, <hi>I beſeech thee, O Lord, remember now how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 20.3.</note> 
               <hi>and haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> Sinne is the very ſting of afflictions. <hi>He,</hi> ſayth <hi>Chryſologus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qui innoc entiae creditum ſeruat paenitentiae non ſoluit vſuram <hi>Chryſol.</hi> ſer. <hi>167.</hi> Clem. Alex. ſtrom. <hi>1.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that keepes the debt of inocency, needs not pay the vſe of peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency.</hi> It is a ſigne of peace within, when a man ſlights afflictions without. Witneſſe <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, It is the glorifying of a boaſting ſoule indeed, but yet it comes from a good conſcience to be able to diſcourſe againſt thoſe troubles that come vpon vs.</hi> Innocency is a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to our conſciencs, that our afflictions are not puniſhments inflicted vpon vs by GOD for our ſinnes, but trialls of our pacience tending to our greater glory. Thus the good man comforts himſelfe from his innocency both againſt mortall men, and alſo before the immortall God.</p>
            <p>The laſt grace of GOD that giues a good man to inable him to ſatisfie himſelfe, is Hope. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <note place="margin">Hope.</note> This ſatisfies the ſoule of a good man for the preſent, becauſe it perſwades him vpon good ground that it will goe better with him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. So that, although now it bee not ſo well with him as hee could wiſh, yet becauſe hee knowes it will bee better, hee reſts ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> compares hope vnto an Egge, <hi>For hope,</hi> ſayth hee, <hi>hath not yet attained the thing it ſelfe. And an Egge is ſomething: but it is
<pb facs="tcp:7937:26"/>not yet a chicken. Beaſts then bring forth yong ones: but Birds bring forth onely hope of yong ones.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ver. Dom ſer. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> The hope then of a good man is ſomewhat, and hath ſome abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to giue him ſatisfaction for the preſent, though it be not ſo much nor cannot ſo well ſatisfie as the glory he hopes for hereafter. It is a morſell to ſtay a good mans ſtomacke, till the feaſt of the Lambes mariage be ready, where he ſhall bee fully ſatisfied. Peraduenture it goes not well with him now, but it will goe well with him one day, and this thought vpholds him. Thus louing <hi>Ionathan</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts deiected <hi>Dauid, Feare not, for the hand of</hi> Saul <hi>my father ſhall not finde thee, and thou ſhalt be King ouer Iſrael, and I ſhall be next vnto thee; and that alſo</hi> Saul <hi>my father knoweth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 23.17.</note> So the good man knowes, and his aduerſaries are not altogether ignorant, that heauen is prepared for him, and therewithall he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfies himſelfe. A yong Prince brought vp vnder tutours and diſciplined by meaner men then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, yet reſts ſatisfied, becauſe he liues in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Kingdome. So doe Gods Princes being exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by wicked men looke vp to heauen, and quiet themſelues. <hi>Moſes</hi> loſt his honours in <hi>Egypt</hi> and his pleaſures to ſuffer afflictions with the Iſraelits, <hi>Eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the reproach of Chriſt greater riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>then the treaſurs in Egypt: for he had reſpect to the recompence of the reward.</hi> There is a hope of worldly preferments, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brings ſhame, becauſe men hope for that they neuer attaine.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.2.5.</note> But <hi>this hope of the glory of God,</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtification, <hi>maketh not aſhamed,</hi> for ſuch perſons neuer miſſe of that they hope for. Thus many ſtrings hath a good man to his bow, and euery one helpes to
<pb facs="tcp:7937:26"/>further his ſelfe-ſatisfaction. If a threeſold cable cannot be eaſily broken, how ſhall an eightfold? So many graces of Gods Spirit linked together in one ſoule cannot but make it able to ſatisfie it ſelfe, if need bee, without helpe of others. For each of theſe hath his ſeuerall force, and therefore as being ioyned together they are the ſtronger, ſo each one putting forth his owne vigour, what cannot be done by one, is done by another. As the Phyſitian ioynes many things in one potion, that what one thing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not helpe, another may, ſo God ioynes many graces in a good mans ſoule, that where one grace cannot giue him ſatisfaction for the preſent, another may. There is not any truth of GOD ſo vndenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but many things may bee, yea many things haue beene by erronious ſpirits obiected againſt it. So this truth of GOD ſo honourable to God and ſo comfortable to man hath not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many engines to batter it, yet it will ſtand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> it hath beene obiected that Gods ſeruants haue beene ſo farre from giuing ſatiſfaction to themſelues, that they haue beene glad to begge of others food and other neceſſaryes for their ſatiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. So <hi>Dauid</hi> was faine to ſend to <hi>Nabal</hi> for food for himſelfe and his men and was ſhamefully deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.4. &amp;c.</note> So <hi>Lazarus</hi> was forced to begge of the Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the crummes that fell from his Table and was cruelly ſtarued by his denyall.<note place="margin">Luke. 16.21.</note> A man would thinke that <hi>Nabal</hi> were better able to giue himſelfe ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction then <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the Rich-man then <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus.</hi> How can this ſtand with ſelfe ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:27"/>
            <p> I anſwere, a good man may bee without many outward comforts, but yet hee hath an internall contentation, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> which hee can oppoſe againſt all outward wants and vphold himſelfe againſt them all. If <hi>Dauid</hi> haue none of <hi>Naballs</hi> victualls, yet he and his men ſhall bee prouided for. If <hi>Lazarus</hi> dye for lacke of the Rich-mans crummes, yet hee dyes contentedly, and is by Angells conuayed to eternall happineſſe. There bee many things which a good man hath not, but there is nothing which hee wants. For he that is well contented with what hee hath,<note place="margin">Diues a Dinus, quia vt Deus nihil indigere videtur. Varro de ling. Lat. <hi>lib. 4.</hi> Locuples est, qui paupertati ſuae aptus eſt, et par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo ſe diuitem fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Sen. ep. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> cannot bee ſaid to want any thing that hee hath not. A Rich-man therefore that hath enough for all vſes, is called in Latine <hi>Diues</hi> from <hi>Diuus, a God,</hi> becauſe like to God, hee ſeemes to ſtand in need of nothing. Let <hi>Seneca</hi> the heathen man tell how a poore man may be rich, and a man of a meane eſtate wealthy. <hi>He is wealthy whoſe mind is fitted to his pouerty, and who hath made himſelfe rich hauing but ſmall poſſeſſions.</hi> If a heathen man could thus teach a poore man, how to make himſelfe rich, much more may the Scriptures informe him. Who counts the Apoſtles of our Lord and Sauiour poore, though they had forſaken all and followed Chriſt, when hee ſees how rich they were in fayth and miracles, but eſpecially in ſweet contentment? Let S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeake for the reſt,<note place="margin">Hôs mêden, echon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i pania cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chontes. <hi>2 Cor. 6.10.</hi>
               </note> and ſay what the Apoſtles were, <hi>as hauing nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> Shall we count the Angels and bleſſed Spirits in heauen poore, becauſe they haue no meate nor drinke, nor apparrell? The Saints had more apparrell, when they were on earth, and more food, yet they were much poorer, then they
<pb facs="tcp:7937:27"/>are now in heauen where they haue none. But to mount vp to the example of examples, who can deny God himſelfe to be rich? <hi>For euery beaſt of the Forreſt is his,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſame 50.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the cattell vpon a thouſand hills.</hi> All men receiue all their treaſures from him, yet he himſelfe heapeth vp no gold nor ſiluer. A good man then that is moſt like God of all his creatures, ſomewhat reſembles his Maieſty in this, that he can be rich, although he lay vp no money. His internall contentment makes him wealthy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though externall things flow not in ſo plentifully to him as vnto others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may bee obiected, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> that good men in their paſſions doe by their words and outward geſtures declare, that they are not internally ſatiſfied. The trembling of their bodies doth in imminent perills bewray the feare of their mindes. The teares iſſuing out of their eyes in calamityes falne vpon them, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth to others the greefe of their harts. How far then are theſe from ſelfe-ſatiſfaction?</p>
            <p>We deny not, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> but a good man may be troubled with greefe or feare for a time. He hath not changed his nature but is as ſenſible of miſery as he was before. His body is as tender: his heart as melting as any mans els. Beſides the ſame ſubſtance of nature, which likes not to be afflicted, he hath the ſame corruption of nature in ſome part remaining, which makes him too ſenſible of worldly vnkindneſſes, and too lyable to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations, and wiles.</p>
            <p>No maruaile then if at ſome time the Diuell doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile him, and vrge him ſo that he ſhew forth his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections to the world, and his diſcontent vnto his neyghbours. But yet wee ſay though the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb facs="tcp:7937:28"/>channell of his owne imperfections clog his heart for a time, yet is there pure water of Gods grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſufficient to giue him ſatisfaction without going to other mens riuers, if he doe but recollect his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: he hath matter enough to ſatisfie him within him, although his troubled ſpirit cannot diſcerne for the preſent how to vſe it. A while after when his paſſion is as an ague fit vaniſhed away, then can he by meditation recall his wandring thoughts, bring them into order and ſettle them by the helpe of his patience and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and other forenamed vertues lodged in his owne breſt by the finger of God. So then for all this bullet, the fort of ſelfe-ſatisfaction cannot be pierced.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> it is obiected, a godly man cannot ſubſiſt neither naturally nor ſpiritually in this life without the helpe of Gods creatures. If he want food, he will be ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. If he want drinke, he will be choaked. If he want apparell, he will be chilled to death. What needed God to haue made ſo many creatures for mans vſe, if they were able to giue ſatisfaction to themſelues? For his ſpirituall ſtate what comfort could he haue to come into Gods Church, if water in baptiſme did not aſſure him of the pardon of his ſinnes? What hope could he haue of heauen if Bread and Wine in the Lords ſupper did not aſſure him that Chriſt dyed for him, and that by fayth in him he may attaine life euerlaſting? How can he be ſayd to bee able to giue ſatisfaction to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hath neede of ſo many creatures for the ſtay of his naturall and ſpirituall condition?</p>
            <p>For anſwere hereunto, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> we muſt take notice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a godly man can be ſafe and may be ſaued without theſe helpes. But God hath giuen him theſe, for to make his
<pb facs="tcp:7937:28"/>paſſage the more comfortable. His creatures hee hath afforded him both for aliment for his naturall life, and props to vphold his fayth for the comfort of his ſoule. If he want Gods creatures for the vpholding of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life, he knowes that eyther God will vphold him without theſe, for <hi>Man liueth not by bread alone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God:</hi> Or elſe God will take him to his heauenly Kingdome, where he ſhall need none of theſe. If he be denyed the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he knows that God can ſaue him without them ſo he haue true fayth in Chriſt. He knows Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is good though no ſeale bee ſet to it. It is not in Gods couenant as it is in mens. Seales are not ſet to for feare of any vnfaythfulnes in God that promiſeth, but becauſe of the weakenes of our fayth in giuing credit to Gods promiſes. The good man then well weighing Gods power and Gods promiſe can vphold himſelfe in the want of bodily foode and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is obiected, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>4</label> that a good man cannot giue ſatisfaction to himſelfe, for then all gouernment in Church and Commonwealth would be ouerthrowne. A good man cannot liue peaceably without the helpe of the Magiſtrate. Nay he needs the helpe of Princes more then other men, becauſe the world hates him, and his religion forbids him reuenge by reaſon whereof e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wicked man will play vpon him, and ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ready to oppreſſe him.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> Therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs to pray, <hi>For Kings, and for all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlines and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</hi> Moreouer a good man cannot liue well without Miniſters to inſtruct him in Gods will. To this end God hath appointed <hi>Paſtours and Teachers</hi> for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:7937:29"/>vp the Saints till we come to perfection of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Chriſt, that wee may not be <hi>carried about with euery wind of doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe 4.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> Without theſe politicall and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall helpes a good man cannot ſubſiſt. How can this ſtand with ſelfe-ſatisfaction? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> True it is a good man receiues much comfort from both theſe, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God for them with all his heart. Yet hee can ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelfe alſo without them. As in the times of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions by heathniſh Emperours when ſuch were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their liberty, ſhut vp in dungeons, denied the benefit of ſubiects, and the freedome of the Goſpell preached: nay if both were his enemies; the Magiſtrate ſeekes the ruine of his body, and the Miniſter of his ſoule, if the one ſhould mightily oppreſſe him, and the other craftily ſeduce him. Yet a good man wold vphold and ſatisfie himſelfe with that ſtore of grace that God hath planted in him before, and hold on without both theſe, nay in deſpight of them, till he attaine to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vnlooked for vpon earth, or glory vnſpeakeable in heauen. All theſe cannons then nor whatſoeuer elſe the diuell can inuent are not able to beate downe the caſtle of ſelfe-ſatisfaction. But it ſtands firme, and will ſtand to the end, that how ſoeuer things alter in the world, a good man will be able to ſatisfie himſelfe with thoſe graces that God hath giuen him, and ſo to ſtand vpon his owne bottome, when great and rich mens eſtates come tottering downe to the ground, and no man can vphold them. Thus haue we wandred vp and downe the garden of the ſoule to view thoſe ſweete flowers that giue contentment to a good man, and thoſe medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble herbes that helpe him to cure all the maladies of his ſoule. All which grow within the wals of his owne
<pb facs="tcp:7937:29"/>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that they may be ready for ſeruice when ill ſauours or ſpirituall diſtempers ſhall oppreſſe the ſoule. Now are we to come to ſhut vp all with application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> from theſe flowers a good man may gather the hony of comfort to carry home to the hiue of his ſoule to feed vpon in the winter of diſcontent.<note place="margin">For comfore.</note> It tels him he hath attained to the beſt condition in the world. There can be no better ſtate, then for a man to be filled with grace from aboue, that he be able in time of need to vphold, nay to ſatisfie himſelfe without the helpe of any other creature. Nay that he bee able to ſtand his owne ground and to make good his owne condition in deſpight of the ſubtilty of all crafty politicians, and the power and malice of all worldly tyrants. Nay in deſpight of all creatures and which are the moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all creatures, and moſt malicious, of the gates of hell. He is a member of the Church which is built vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rocke,<note place="margin">Math. 16.18.</note> and therefore <hi>the gates of hell cannot preuaile againſt him.</hi> When he ſeeth troubles ſpirituallor corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall approach vnto him, then let him looke inward, and gather together the forces of his ſoule, and then may he boldly looke dangers in the face, and not feare to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome them: Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> oppreſſed with many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies comforts himſelfe againſt them, and lies downe quietly without feare of them, <hi>I layd me downe and ſlept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 35, 6.</note> 
               <hi>I awaked for the Lord ſuſtained me. I will not be afraid of ten thouſands of people, that haue ſet themſelues againſt me round about.</hi> So is the ſeruant of God by Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes made as it were <hi>a little God vpon earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cultum tantùm Deo deberi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus, qui verus eſt Deus, facit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuos cultores Deos. <hi>Aug.</hi> de ciu, Dei. l. <hi>10.</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> able through Gods grace to ſtand of himſelfe againſt all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to ſatisfie himſelfe in all occurrents. O happy condition, and moſt happy man that hath attained to it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7937:30"/>
            <p> Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> a good man may from hence receiue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular direction.<note place="margin">For direction.</note> Let him not hunt for felicity abroad in the world, which hee may finde at home within his owne wals. Who would not begge him for a foole that hauing a fountaine of his owne at hand, would run to other mens to ſeeke for water? So vaine a thing is it for a man to ſeeke for ſatisfaction from the wealth or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the world abroad which he might find much more comfortably, and infallibly from his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience within doores. For when all the wealth of the world cannot ſatisfie the minde, peace of conſcience can. Let other men ſeeke with all eagernes for worldly commodities, &amp; place their ſole ſatisfaction in them. <hi>Dauid</hi> will place it in Gods fauour. With the light of thy countenance <hi>Thou haſt put gladnes in my heart more then in the time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>that their corne and their wine increaſed.</hi> Shew thou thy ſelfe a good man by thy contentednes, when thou wanteſt outward comforts and riches in the world. Looke vpon the wide ſea, behold how euery day it ſends forth plenty of waters into all the riuers about it, &amp; daily takes them backe againe, yet is the ſea neuer dry, neither doth it euer want water. Goe thou and doe likewiſe. Shew thy ſelfe as well ſatisfied when floods of wealth are flowed from thee, as when ſprings of riches run vnto thee. So ſhalt thou bee to the world a proofe of the text, and an example of ſelfe-ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> it may informe wicked men what tickle termes they ſtand vpon,<note place="margin">For informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and how great a miſchiefe the want of goodnes is: their conſcience is vnquiet perhaps. Al the world cannot giue them ſatiſfaction who might receiue it from their owne conſciences, if they were good and feared God. Perhaps their conſcience is quiet
<pb facs="tcp:7937:30"/>for the preſent. So may the ſea be for a time, but euery little wind will moue it and ſuddenly make it rage. <hi>The wicked are like the troubled Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 57.20.21</note> 
               <hi>when it cannot reſt whoſe waters caſt vp mire and dirt. There is no peace ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi> So miſerable is the condition of a wicked man, that he hath no aſſurance of quietneſſe, nor no ſolid ſatiſfaction in vnquietneſſe of mind. They that want goodnes are no where aſſured to remaine quiet, much leſſe are they able to giue ſatiſfaction to themſelues for this is a good mans priuiledge, and a wicked man hath no ſhare in it. So the want of goodnes both layes a man open to a world of miſchiefes, and alſo depriues him of all meanes of ſelfe-ſatiſfaction.</p>
            <p>Laſtly <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> all that hath beene ſpoken may ſerue for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation,<note place="margin">For prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to ſtirre vp euery one with all his might to ſeeke after goodneſſe. This is the onely way to ſelfe-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction. A wicked man when his goods are loſt, raues and rages, as if he had loſt all his happines. A goodman quiets himſelfe with holy <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>Naked came I out of my mothers wombe: and naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord gaue, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> A wicked man when his body is ſicke, and he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with paine, and in feare of death, quakes for feare of hell torments. A goodman concluds with <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>We know that if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle were diſolued, we haue a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the Heauens.</hi> A wicked man when his friends for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him,<note place="margin">So the words are in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew. Hee meanes that Chriſt will plead for him to God the Father. Iob. 16.20.21.</note> cryes out againſt the perfidiouſneſſe of this age and the vnfaithfullneſſe of the world. A good man lookes vp vnto God in Chriſt as <hi>Iob</hi> did before him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>My friends are my ſcorners: but mine eye powreth out teares vnto God. And he will pleade for man with God, and
<pb facs="tcp:7937:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Sunne of man for his friend.</hi> A wicked man when wars rage and the trumpets ſound in his eares, and the ſword glitters in his eyes, finds his heart dead within him like <hi>Naballs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.37. Pſalme 46.1.2.</note> A good man reſolues with <hi>Dauid, God is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and ſtrength: a very preſent helpe in trouble. Therfore will I not feare, though the earth be remoued: &amp; though the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines be carried into the midſt of the Sea.</hi> Behold a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand of himſelfe, when Mountaines are mooued, and to giue himſelfe ſatiſfaction, when the ſtable earth is fleeting. A good man is like a die, throw it which way you will, it is alwayes ſquare: ſo is a good man euer the ſame in his maine and generall carriage, how euer for the preſent he may be daunted at ſome ſudden accident vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for in the world.<note place="margin">Stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus vt luna mutatur: ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens vt, ſol. In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le et f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruor et ſplendor ſtabilis in luna ſolus ſplendor, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> is ommino <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilis et incertus qui nunquam in eodem ſtatu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneat. Ber de Beata. Mar.</note> 
               <hi>The foole,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, is change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able like the Moone: but the wiſe man is conſtant like the Sun. In the Sun there is both heate and brightnes conſtant, in the Moone onely brightnes, and that altogether mutable &amp; vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as neuer remaining in any condition.</hi> In al the creatures God hath placed ſomewhat to proue them to bee his: ſomwhat to reſemble him and ſomwhat aboue the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of any creature to infuſe, that it might appeare to be Gods workmanſhip: eſpecially in a good man God hath placed ſelfe-ſatiſfaction, whereby hee is moſt like his Creatour, and which none could put into him but God, that God might haue all the glory of it. To conclude, goodnes and ſelfe-ſatiſfaction, holines &amp; happines goe together.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel. 20:6.</hi> Indè beatus vndè bonus Aug. ep. <hi>121.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</hi> On which words S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhortly and ſweetly comments, <hi>He is therefore happy, becauſe he is good.</hi> wouldſt thou then be ſafe? Get goodnes that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt haue ſelfe-ſatiſfaction in this world, and thou ſhalt be ſure of eternall hapineſſe in the world to come.</p>
            <closer>Which God grant euery one of vs, through Ieſus Chriſt, our Sauiour, Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
